Finding Aid for Ann Arbor Symphony Orchestra Records, 1931-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ann Arbor Symphony Orchestra Records 1931-2003
Ann Arbor Symphony Orchestra.
6 linear feet
8555 Bp/2
This record group contains the records of the Ann Arbor Symphony Orchestra, the Women's Association for the Ann Arbor Symphony, and partial records for the Michigan Civic Orchestra Association. The record group includes administrative and functional records, photographs, and audio/visual concert recordings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The major corpus of records were donated by the Ann Arbor Symphony (Donor no. 6653 ) on August 27, 2004.
The record group is open to research.
The Ann Arbor Symphony Orchestra began in 1928 as the Ann Arbor Orchestra with only 5 or 6 players. In 1931, the group called themselves the Ann Arbor Community Orchestra and performed their first concert on November 30. By 1935, the orchestra had grown to 40 players, joined with the Ann Arbor Recreation Department, and became known as the Ann Arbor Civic Orchestra.
From 1935 to 1985, the Ann Arbor Civic Orchestra, renamed the Ann Arbor Civic Symphony Orchestra in 1952, provided concerts free of charge to the Ann Arbor Community in area school auditoriums, the Hill Auditorium at the University of Michigan, the Michigan Theater, and the West Park Shell in Ann Arbor's West Park. The Orchestra maintained a commitment to Ann Arbor artists, to encouraging youth involvement in music, and bringing live, classical symphonic music to the city of Ann Arbor. They often teamed with other artistic and musical organizations like the Women's Chorale and the Ann Arbor Civic Ballet. By 1981, the Orchestra had grown to 100 members During this time, the Orchestra had ten conductors, Warren Ketcham (1929-1931), Frederick Ernst (1931-1933), William Champion (1933-1941), Joseph Maddy (1941-1951), Orien Dalley (1951-1955), Emil Raab (1955-1957), George C. Wilson (1957-1961), William Fitch (1961-1963), Emil Holz (1963-1972), and Edward Szabo (1972-1985).
Throughout its history, the A2SO has relied upon the donations of area philanthropists and since 1952, the efforts of the Women's Association. However, starting in the late 1960's and certainly by the 1970's, these monies alone could not keep up with the rising operational cost of the Orchestra. To raise funds, the Orchestra began hosting events to raise both money and awareness of the orchestra. However, the financial problems persisted. In 1985, in a controversial decision that coincided with the somewhat abrupt replacement of Conductor Edward Szabo with Carl St. Clair, the A2SO began charging admission for concerts. This move quickly resulted in a much larger budget from marketing campaigns and ticket sales. The increased budget allowed the Orchestra to attain a higher standard of professionalism, attracting better musicians and soloists, performing more concerts, and bolstering its reputation in Ann Arbor and nationally. Conductors Samuel Wong (1992-1999) and Arie Lipsky (2000-2006) have continued this tradition.
The Women's Association of the Ann Arbor Symphony was formed in 1952 with the goal of assisting with concerts, providing refreshments for players at rehearsals, and raising money both for the Orchestra and for music scholarships for area youth.
The Michigan Civic Orchestra Association began in Ann Arbor in 1939. By 1960, the organization of Michigan orchestras included over 30 community orchestras. It hosted annual meetings and several massed orchestra festivals.
The Ann Arbor Symphony Orchestra (AASO) records document the founding and development of the orchestra and the Women's Association for the Ann Arbor Symphony. There are also some records of the Michigan Civic Orchestra Association. The records include administrative and functional records, photographs, and audio/visual concert recordings. The records are arranged into 11 series, History, Board of Directors, Symphony Business, Youth Activities, Fundraising, Publicity, Women's Association of the Ann Arbor Symphony (WA3S) Records, Michigan Civic Orchestra Association, Visual Materials, Scrapbooks, and Audio Materials.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Symphony Orchestra.; Arts--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies, etc.; Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Musicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Michigan Civic Orchestra Association.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor Symphony Orchestra.; Concerts.; Conductors.; Dancers.; Dance.; Holz, Emil Aaron.; Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Musical instruments.; Orchestras.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Ann Arbor Symphony Orchestra.
Contributors:
Women's Association of the Ann Arbor Symphony.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- History
  The History series (0.1 linear feet) contains documents defining the symphony, telling the history, and documenting anniversaries.
  - Mission and Purpose of A2SO 1972-1988 (Box 1)
  - General History 1950-1992 (Box 1)
  - 50th Anniversary Documents 1978 (Box 1)
  - 65th Anniversary Documents 1993 (Box 1)
  - 75th Anniversary Documents 2003 (Box 1)
- Board of Directors
  The Board of Directors series (0.8 linear feet) functions as an administrative series, including the constitution and by-laws of the board, Meetings and Reports to the Board, Activities of Committees, Financial materials, and Topical files
  - Role, Functions and Responsibilities of the Board (Box 1)
  - Constitution and By-Laws 1942-1988 (Box 1)
  - Affirmative Action Policy 1984 (Box 1)
  - Meetings and Reports
    - Rosters 1950-1994 (Box 1)
    - Annual Meetings 1953-1993 (Box 1)
    - Meeting Minutes and Agendas 1950-1994, 9 folders (Box 1)
    - Long Range Plans 1980-1994 (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Committee Assignments 1957-1984 (Box 1)
    - Ad Hoc Committee for Youth Soloist Competition 1972 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee Authority 1970, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes and Agendas 1960-1994, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Fundraising 1963-1966 (Box 1)
    - Committees on Goals 1976 (Box 1)
    - Marketing 1988 (Box 1)
    - Nominating 1955-1992 (Box 1)
    - Outreach and Education 1990-1994 (Box 1)
    - Special Events 1988-1992 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1971-1992 (Box 1)
  - Financial
    - Budgets and Statements 1950-1995, 9 folders (Box 1)
    - Financial Consultant 1974 (Box 1)
    - Financial Charts 1985-1993 (Box 1)
    - 4 Point Plan 1991 (Box 1)
  - Topical
    - Ann Arbor Recreation Department 1933-1974 (Box 1)
    - Briarwood Merchants Association 1975 (Box 1)
    - Board of Education Correspondence 1943-1951 (Box 1)
    - Dramatic Arts Center 1954, 1959 (Box 1)
    - General Correspondence 1950-1979 (Box 1)
    - Roger Jacobi Outgoing Letters 1958 (Box 1)
    - Phillip Potts Outgoing Letters 1950-1952 (Box 1)
    - Resignations 1951-1989 (Box 1)
    - Edward Szabo 1984 (Box 1)
    - Women's Association of the Ann Arbor Symphony 1954-1973 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Symphony Business
  Symphony Business (0.3 linear feet) covers the day-to day operations of the symphony, including information about members, and documents relating to rehearsals and concerts. This series corresponds with "Symphony Business" and "Performances" sub-sub-series of Visual Materials, Photographs and with the entire Audio Materials series.
  - Personnel
    - Orchestra Rosters 1947-1984 (Box 1)
    - Conductor Search 1964, 1972, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Players 1950-1993 (Box 1)
    - American Federation of Musicians 1970-1992 (Box 1)
  - Rehearsals and Concerts
    - Attendance Records 1937-1955 (Box 1)
    - Rehearsal Schedules 1954-1994 (Box 1)
    - Concerts 1936-1989 (Box 1)
    - Programs 1944-1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Programs 1973-1993, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Youth Activities
  Youth Activities (0.1 linear feet) relates to the interaction between the A2SO and Ann Arbor youth. These include Soloist and Scholarship activities as well as program notes created by the conductor for distribution to area school teachers. From 1986 to 2003, program notes were distributed with the concert programs. This series corresponds with the "Youth" sub-sub-series of Visual Materials, Photographs.
  - Youth Soloists 1961-1965, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Scholarships 1948-1962, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Youth Concerts 1960-1965 (Box 2)
  - Invitations to Teachers 1976 (Box 2)
  - Program Notes,1965-1973 1989-1993 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Fundraising
  The Fundraising series (0.3 linear feet) documents the work of the A2SO to generate income through contribution, subscription, and later season ticket sales, and major events in the Ann Arbor area. This series corresponds with the "Community" sub-sub-series of Visual Materials, Photographs.
  - Campaigns
    - Annual Brochures 1953-1994 (Box 2)
    - Contributions 1952-1994, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Grant Proposals 1972-1992 (Box 2)
    - Ticket Sales 1984-1992 (Box 2)
  - Events
    - Leonard Rose Concert 1975 (Box 2)
    - Ypsilanti Concerts 1976 (Box 2)
    - Symphony Balls 1965-1979 (Box 2)
    - Flower Sales 1981-1993 (Box 2)
    - Events 1964-1993 (Box 2)
    - "Volunteam" Volunteer Work 1981-1991 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Publicity
  Publicity (0.4 linear feet) includes internal documentation of the efforts for publicity, Symphony Newsletters, posters and other professionally produced promotional material as well as newspaper clippings including advertising, reviews of concerts, and public conversations by letters to the editor.
  - Internal Documents 1950-1979 (Box 2)
  - Symphony Notes [Newsletter] 1980-1993 (Box 2)
  - Posters (Box 2)
  - Brochures, Mailings, Handouts (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Advertisements 1937-1994 (Box 2)
    - Articles 1937-1994, 10 folders (Box 2)
- Women's Association of the Ann Arbor Symphony Records
  The Women's Association of the Ann Arbor Symphony (WA3S) Records (0.2 linear feet) document the activities of the Women's Association from 1950 to 1983
  - By-Laws 1956-1970 (Box 2)
  - State Documents 1976-1977 (Box 2)
  - Brochures undated (Box 2)
  - Rosters 1963-1983 (Box 2)
  - Yearbooks 1957-1983 (Box 2)
  - Board Meeting Minutes and Agendas 1957-1983 (Box 3)
  - Meetings (Not Board) 1955-1978 (Box 3)
  - Treasurer Reports 1950-1979 (Box 3)
  - Reports 1958-1965 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters 1957-1982 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence
    - Other Women's Symphony Organizations 1965-1969 (Box 3)
    - General 1950-1979 (Box 3)
  - Concert Activities 1967-1969 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Michigan Civic Orchestra Association
  The Michigan Civic Orchestra Association series (0.1 linear feet) is a short, incomplete collection of records from the MCOA from 1944 until 1972
  - By-Laws and Constitution 1944-1964 (Box 3)
  - Member Orchestras 1950-1968 (Box 3)
  - Meetings 1951-1969 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters 1958-1975 (Box 3)
  - Massed Orchestra Festival 1951-1952 (Box 3)
  - Women's Association Records 1967-1972 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series (1.8 linear feet) is arranged first by format into three sub-series, Photographs, Negatives, and VHS Cassette Tapes. The photographs are further arranged by subject into four sub-sub-series, Symphony Business, including photographs of orchestra members and behind-the-scenes activities, Performances, Community including photographs from fundraising and charitable events, and Youth including photographs of the interaction between the A2SO and the youth of the Southeast Michigan area. Negatives relates directly to the photographs. Most of the VHS Cassette Tapes are recordings of concerts and are arranged chronologically.
  - Photographs
    - Symphony Business
      - Group Photos 1934-1940 (Box 3)
      - Individuals circa 1963-1972 (Box 3)
      - Rehearsals 1955-1996 (Box 3)
        (Neg. #1 #91847)
      - Vocal Auditions 3/27/1996 (Box 3)
        (Neg. #1)
    - Performances
      - January Concert 1/19/1958 (Box 3)
      - Emil Holz Conducting Undated (1963-1972) (Box 3)
      - Ensemble at Hudson's 1990 (Box 3)
      - Caroling by Candlelight 12/1990 (Box 3)
      - Carl St. Clair Farewell Concert 4/25/1992 (Box 3)
      - 1995/1996 Season (Box 3)
        (Neg #1 #21846 #99075)
      - 1996/1997 Season (Box 3)
        (Neg #"Annex", #3329 #46639 #46640 #46641 #56068 #56069 #57876 #57877 #57878 #57879 #66739 #66740 #94820)
      - 1997/1998 Season (Box 3)
        (Neg #12557 #12558 #30290 #30290A, #30291 #66988 #91506 #91507)
      - 1998/1999 Season (Box 3)
        (Neg #2 #3, #4, #1830 #3003 #30002 #46833 #95047)
      - Samuel Wong Conducting 1992-1999, undated (Box 3)
    - Community
      - Symphony Ball, Early 1970s (Box 3)
      - Symphony Sprint 5/29/1981 (Box 3)
      - Women's Association of the Ann Arbor Symphony Donations 11/1983 (Box 3)
      - Tailgate Party 1990-1992 (Box 3)
        (Neg #76239 #9111)
      - Flower Sales 1968, 1991-1996 (Box 3)
        (Neg #50959)
      - Golf Outings 1994-1999 (Box 3)
        (Neg #09377)
      - Receptions 4/24/1998 (Box 3)
        (Neg #30289)
      - Hearts for the Arts 2/14/1997 (Box 3)
        (Neg #56068)
    - Youth
      - Youth Scholarship Winners 3/19/1984 (Box 3)
      - Ensembles in the Classroom 1996-1999 (Box 3)
        (Neg #3539 #21432 #31327 #77636 #96426)
      - Mentorship Receptions 1996-1998 (Box 3)
        (Neg #5, #19378 #45549 #69021)
      - Sing Along with Santa 1996-1998 (Box 3)
        (Neg #34367 #34368 #54306 #54307)
      - Petting Zoo 1991 (Box 3)
        (Neg #6, #7, #8, #9, #45624a, #45624b, #45810)
  - Negatives
    - "Annex"-49999 (Box 3)
    - 50000-99999 (Box 3)
    - Photo log (Box 3)
  - Videotapes (VHS cassettes)
    - January 15, 1989-January 24, 2000, 11 videocassettes VHS (Box 4)
    - Sam Wong on Sunday Morning News, Spring 1992 (Box 4)
    - You Should Join the A2 Symphony undated (Box 4)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbooks series (1 linear foot), dating from 1931 to 1968, contains a lot of the early documentation of the A2SO, then the Ann Arbor Civic Orchestra or the Ann Arbor Community Orchestra and the Women's Association.
  - Orchestra
    - October 1931-June 1936 (Box 5)
    - September 1936-1946, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - 1947-1959, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 5)
  - Women's Association of the Ann Arbor Symphony
    - 1952-1968 (Box 5)
      (8 volumes)
- Audio Materials
  The Audio Materials series (1 linear foot) contains 112 cassette tapes of concerts from 1974 until 2000.
  - October 11, 1974-April 24, 1993, 61 audiocassettes (Box 6)
  - September 11, 1993-April 29, 2000, 51 audiocassettes (Box 7)